So, how many of you have ever
بادئ ذي بدء، كم شخص منكم
gotten behind the wheel of a car
قام بقيادة سيارة
when you really shouldn't have been driving?
في حين أنّه غير مسموح له بالقيادة؟
Maybe you're out on the road for a long day,
ربّما كنت خارج المنزل طوال اليوم،
and you just wanted to get home.
و أردت فقط أن تعود إليه.
You were tired, but you felt you could drive a few more miles.
كنت متعبا و مع ذلك شعرت بأن لديك القدرة على قيادة المزيد من الأميال الإضافية.
Maybe you thought,
قد تكون فكّرت
I've had less to drink than everybody else,
بأنّك تناولت كحولا أقلّ من الآخرين،
I should be the one to go home.
لذا أنت من الذي يتوجب عليه العودة للمنزل.
Or maybe your mind was just entirely elsewhere.
أو قد قد يكون عقلك مشغولاً في أمر آخر.
Does this sound familiar to you?
هل تبدو هذه الأحداث مألوفةً لكم ؟
Now, in those situations, wouldn't it be great
في مثل هذه الحالات، ألن يكون أمرا رائعا
if there was a button on your dashboard
أن يوجد زرّ في لوحة قيادة السيّارة والذي
that you could push, and the car would get you home safely?
بعد الضغط عليه تأخذك السيارة مباشرةً للمنزل بكل أمان ؟
Now, that's been the promise of the self-driving car,
حالياً هذا هو المتوقع من سيارات القيادة الذاتية،
the autonomous vehicle, and it's been the dream
"المركبات ذاتية التحكم" و قد وجد هذا الحلم
since at least 1939, when General Motors showcased
منذ مالايقل عن عام 1939، حين عرضت جنرال موتورز
this idea at their Futurama booth at the World's Fair.
هذه الفكرة في جناحها فيوتشراما "أفكار مستقبلية" في المعرض العالمي.
Now, it's been one of those dreams
كان هذا الحلم يبدو مثل أحد الأحلام
that's always seemed about 20 years in the future.
التي تبدو دائماً أنها ستتحقّق في العشرين سنة القادمة.
Now, two weeks ago, that dream took a step forward,
و لكن منذ أسبوعين تقدّم هذا الحلم خطوة،
when the state of Nevada granted Google's self-driving car
حين منحت ولاية نيفادا سيارة غوغل ذاتية القايادة
the very first license for an autonomous vehicle,
أول رخصة من نوعها لسيارة ذاتية التحكم،
clearly establishing that it's legal for them
موضّحة أنّهم يعترفون بها قانونيّا
to test it on the roads in Nevada.
للاختبار على الطرق في ولاية نيفادا.
Now, California's considering similar legislation,
الآن، تفكّر ولاية كاليفورنيا في تشريعات مماثلة،
and this would make sure that the autonomous car
وهذا سوف يجعل بكل تأكيد سيارة التحكم الذاتي
is not one of those things that has to stay in Vegas.
واحدة من تلك الأشياء التي لا تبقى في لاس فيجاس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, in my lab at Stanford, we've been working on
الآن، في مختبري بجامعة ستانفورد، لقد قمنا بالعمل ايضاً على
autonomous cars too, but with a slightly different spin
السيارات ذاتية التحكم، ولكن بطريقة مختلفة
on things. You see, we've been developing robotic race cars,
في بعض الأمور. لقد قمنا بتطوير سيارات السباق روبوتيّة،
cars that can actually push themselves to the very limits
التي يمكن في الواقع أن تتحمّل أبعد من حدود طاقاتها
of physical performance.
من الأداء الحركيّ.
Now, why would we want to do such a thing?
تتساءلون، لماذا نريد القيام بشيء من هذا القبيل؟
Well, there's two really good reasons for this.
حسنا، يوجد هناك سببان جيدّان حقاً.
First, we believe that before people turn over control
أولاً، نحن نعتقد أنه قبل أن يسيطر الناس على
to an autonomous car, that autonomous car should be
السيارة ذاتية التحكم ، ينبغي أن تكون تلك السيارات
at least as good as the very best human drivers.
على الأقل جيدة كجودة أفضل السائقين البشريين.
Now, if you're like me, and the other 70 percent of the population
إذا كنت مثلي، و مثل 70 بالمئة من السكان
who know that we are above-average drivers,
الذين يعرفون بأننا أعلى من السائقين متوسطي القيادة،
you understand that's a very high bar.
فأنك تفهم أن هذا مستوى عالي جداً.
There's another reason as well.
و يوجد هناك سبب آخر أيضا.
Just like race car drivers can use all of the friction
مثلما هو الحال مع قائدي سيارات السباق الذين بإستطاعتهم إستخدام كل الإحتكاكات
between the tire and the road,
ما بين الإطارات والطريق،
all of the car's capabilities to go as fast as possible,
و كل قدرة السيارة للإنطلاق بأسرع سرعة ممكنه،
we want to use all of those capabilities to avoid
فنحن نريد أن نستخدم كل تلك القدرات لتجنّب
any accident we can.
أيّ حادث.
Now, you may push the car to the limits
يمكنك أن تدفع السيارة إلى آخر حدود طاقاتها
not because you're driving too fast,
ليس لأنك تقود بسرعة عالية جداً،
but because you've hit an icy patch of road,
ولكن لأنك قد اصدمت ببقعة جليدية على الطريق،
conditions have changed.
فتغيرت الظروف.
In those situations, we want a car
وفي تلك الحالات، نريد سيارة
that is capable enough to avoid any accident
قادرة بما يكفي لتجنب أي حادث
that can physically be avoided.
قد يمكن تجنبه.
I must confess, there's kind of a third motivation as well.
يجب أن أعترف، يوجد هناك دافع ثالث كذلك.
You see, I have a passion for racing.
كما ترون، لديّ شغف لسباق السيارات.
In the past, I've been a race car owner,
لقد كنت مالكا لسيارة سباق في الماضي،
a crew chief and a driving coach,
رئيس طاقم ومدرب لقيادة السيارات،
although maybe not at the level that you're currently expecting.
ولكن ربما على مستوى أقل من ما تتوقعونه حالياً.
One of the things that we've developed in the lab --
واحدة من الأمور التي قمنا بتطويرها في المختبر--
we've developed several vehicles --
لقد قمنا بتطوير عدد من المركبات --
is what we believe is the world's first
التي نعتقد بأنها أوّل سيارة في العالم
autonomously drifting car.
تقوم بالانجراف الذاتي.
It's another one of those categories
هذا المجال يعتبر واحد من تلك المجالات
where maybe there's not a lot of competition.
حيث ربما لا توجد الكثير من المنافسة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this is P1. It's an entirely student-built electric vehicle,
لكن هذه هي P1. إنّها سيارة كهربائية كلياً بنيت من قبل طالب،
which through using its rear-wheel drive
ومن خلال استخدام العجلات الخلفية
and front-wheel steer-by-wire
وتوجيه عجلة الجبهة بالأسلاك
can drift around corners.
فإنّ السيارة يمكنها الانجراف حول الزوايا.
It can get sideways like a rally car driver,
يمكنها الإنحراف مثلما يفعل سائق سيارة الرالي،
always able to take the tightest curve,
دائماً قادرة على اتخاذ أشد منحنى،
even on slippery, changing surfaces,
حتى على الأسطح الزلقة، المتغيرة،
never spinning out.
فإنها أبداً لا تنزلق .
We've also worked with Volkswagen Oracle,
لقد عملنا أيضا مع "أوراكل فولكس فاجن"،
on Shelley, an autonomous race car that has raced
في شيلي، على سيارة سباق بالتحكم الذاتي و التي قد سابقت
at 150 miles an hour through the Bonneville Salt Flats,
بسرعة 150 ميلاً في الساعة على مسطحات بونفيل سالت،
gone around Thunderhill Raceway Park in the sun,
وفي مضمار حديقة ثونديرهيل تحت أشعة الشمس،
the wind and the rain,
و في الريح والمطر،
and navigated the 153 turns and 12.4 miles
و عبرت المنعرجات ال 153 و 12.4 ميلاً
of the Pikes Peak Hill Climb route
" Pikes Peak Hill Climb" من طريق
in Colorado with nobody at the wheel.
في كلورادو بدون وجود أيّ شخص خلف المقود.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I guess it goes without saying that we've had a lot of fun
أعتقد أنّني في غنى عن القول بأننّا استمتعنا كثيراً عند
doing this.
قيامنا بذلك.
But in fact, there's something else that we've developed
ولكن في الواقع، هناك شيء آخر قمنا بتطويره
in the process of developing these autonomous cars.
في خلال عملية تطوير هذه السيارات المتمتعة بالتحكم الذاتي.
We have developed a tremendous appreciation
قمنا بتطوير تقدير هائل
for the capabilities of human race car drivers.
لقدرات سائقي السيارات السباق الرياضية.
As we've looked at the question of how well do these cars perform,
عندما نظرنا إلى كيفية أداء هذه السيارات،
we wanted to compare them to our human counterparts.
أردنا مقارنتها مع نظرائنا البشريين.
And we discovered their human counterparts are amazing.
واكتشفنا بأن نظرائهم البشريين فعلاً مدهشون.
Now, we can take a map of a race track,
الآن، يمكن أن نأخذ خريطة لمسار السباق،
we can take a mathematical model of a car,
يمكن أن نأخذ نموذجا حسابيّا لسيارة،
and with some iteration, we can actually find
ومع بعض التكرار، يمكننا أن نجد
the fastest way around that track.
أسرع طريقة حول هذا المسار.
We line that up with data that we record
قارنّا تلك البيانات مع التي نقوم بتسجيلها
from a professional driver,
من سائق محترف،
and the resemblance is absolutely remarkable.
ووجدنا التشابه واضحا بشكل قاطع.
Yes, there are subtle differences here,
نعم، يوجد هناك اختلافات طفيفة هنا،
but the human race car driver is able to go out
ولكن سائق سيارة سباق قادرعلى الخروج
and drive an amazingly fast line,
و القيادة على خط سريع بشكل مدهش،
without the benefit of an algorithm that compares
دون الاستفادة من الخوارزمية التي تقارن
the trade-off between going as fast as possible
المفاضلة بين الذهاب في أسرع وقت ممكن
in this corner, and shaving a little bit of time
من هذه الزاوية، و التّقليل من الوقت
off of the straight over here.
من الخروج بشكل مستقيم من هنا.
Not only that, they're able to do it lap
ليس هذا فقط، باستطاعتهم القيام بذلك دورة
after lap after lap.
بعد دورة بعد دورة.
They're able to go out and consistently do this,
إنّهم قادرون على الخروج والإستمرار في فعل ذلك،
pushing the car to the limits every single time.
دفع السيارة إلى آخر طاقتها كل مرّة .
It's extraordinary to watch.
هذا أمر رائع للمشاهدة.
You put them in a new car,
يمكنك وضعهم في سيارة جديدة،
and after a few laps, they've found the fastest line in that car,
وبعد دورات قليلة، تجدهم قد وجدوا أسرع خط في تلك السيارة،
and they're off to the races.
وبدأوا بالسباقات
It really makes you think,
إنّه حقاً يجعلك تفكّر،
we'd love to know what's going on inside their brain.
أنّك ترغب في معرفة ما الذي يحدث داخل أدمغتهم.
So as researchers, that's what we decided to find out.
لذلك كباحثين، هذا ما قررنا معرفتة.
We decided to instrument not only the car,
قررنا أن لا نصنع السيارة فقط،
but also the race car driver,
بل أيضاَ سائق سيارة سباق،
to try to get a glimpse into what was going on
محاولين الحصول على لمحة إلى ما كان يحدث في
in their head as they were doing this.
في رؤوسهم كلّما كانوا يفعلون هذا.
Now, this is Dr. Lene Harbott applying electrodes
الآن، هذا هو الدكتورلين هاربوت يضع أقطاب
to the head of John Morton.
في رأس جون مورتون.
John Morton is a former Can-Am and IMSA driver,
جون مورتون هو سائق سابق ل Can-Am و IMSA
who's also a class champion at Le Mans.
وهو أيضا بطل فيLe Mans.
Fantastic driver, and very willing to put up with graduate students
سائق رائع، ومستعد جداً لمتابعة طلاب الدراسات العليا
and this sort of research.
وهذا النّوع من البحوث.
She's putting electrodes on his head
تقوم بوضع أقطاب على رأسه
so that we can monitor the electrical activity
لنتمكّن من رصد النشاط الكهربائي
in John's brain as he races around the track.
في الدماغ جون وهو يتسابق حول المضمار.
Now, clearly we're not going to put a couple of electrodes on his head
الآن، ومن الواضح أننا لن نضع اثنين من الأقطاب على رأسه
and understand exactly what all of his thoughts are on the track.
ونفهم بالضبط ما أفكاره كلها على المضمار.
However, neuroscientists have identified certain patterns
ولكن علماء الأعصاب قد حدّدوا أنماط معينة
that let us tease out some very important aspects of this.
مكّنتنا من فصل بعض الجوانب الهامة جداً.
For instance, the resting brain
فعلى سبيل المثال، الدماغ الهادئ
tends to generate a lot of alpha waves.
يميل إلى توليد الكثير من موجات ألفا.
In contrast, theta waves are associated with
وفي المقابل، موجات ثيتا ترتبط مع
a lot of cognitive activity, like visual processing,
الكثير من النشاط الإدراكي, مثل المعالجة المرئية،
things where the driver is thinking quite a bit.
الأشياء التي يفكر فيها السائقً.
Now, we can measure this,
الآن، يمكن أن نقيس هذا،
and we can look at the relative power
ويمكننا أن ننظر إلى القوة النسبية
between the theta waves and the alpha waves.
بين موجات ثيتا وموجات ألفا.
This gives us a measure of mental workload,
وهذا يعطينا مقياسا لجهد العمل العقلي،
how much the driver is actually challenged cognitively
ما هو فعلاً مقدار التحدي الإدراكي للسائق
at any point along the track.
في أي نقطة على طول المضمار.
Now, we wanted to see if we could actually record this
الآن، نريد أن نرى إذا كان يمكننا في الواقع تسجيل هذا
on the track, so we headed down south to Laguna Seca.
على المضمار، لذلك اتجهنا إلى الجنوب إلى لاغونا سيكا.
Laguna Seca is a legendary raceway
لاغونا سيكا هو مضمار سباق أسطوري
about halfway between Salinas and Monterey.
يقع في منتصف الطريق بين ساليناس ومونتيري.
It has a curve there called the Corkscrew.
فيها منحنى يسمى هناك Corkscrew.
Now, the Corkscrew is a chicane, followed by a quick
الآن، Corkscrew عبارة عن منحنيات، يليها
right-handed turn as the road drops three stories.
منحنى حاد في اليمين كلما أنخفض الطريق ثلاث مستويات.
Now, the strategy for driving this as explained to me was,
الآن، استراتيجية القيادة كما تمّ شرحها لي، كانت
you aim for the bush in the distance,
الاتّجاه نحو الشجيرات البعيدة
and as the road falls away, you realize it was actually the top of a tree.
و عند انخفاض الطّريق، تكتشف أنّ ذلك كان في الواقع قمّة شجرة.
All right, so thanks to the Revs Program at Stanford,
على العموم، بفضل برنامج Revs في جامعة ستانفورد،
we were able to take John there
كنا قادرين على أخذ جون هناك
and put him behind the wheel
ووضعه خلف عجلة قيادة
of a 1960 Porsche Abarth Carrera.
بورش البارث كاريرا موديل 1960 .
Life is way too short for boring cars.
الحياة قصيرة جداً للسيارات المملة.
So, here you see John on the track,
لذلك، هنا نرى جون على المضمار
he's going up the hill -- Oh! Somebody liked that --
يأخذ في الصعود إلى أعلى التل--أوه! شخص ما أحب ذلك-
and you can see, actually, his mental workload
ويمكنك أن ترى، في الواقع، جهده العقليّ
-- measuring here in the red bar --
- يقاس هنا في الشريط الأحمر-
you can see his actions as he approaches.
يمكنك أن ترى أفعاله كلما يقترب.
Now watch, he has to downshift.
الآن شاهد، يجب عليه الهبوط في الطّريق.
And then he has to turn left.
ومن ثم يجب عليه التوجّه إلى اليسار.
Look for the tree, and down.
البحث عن الشجرة، وإلى أسفل.
Not surprisingly, you can see this is a pretty challenging task.
وليس من المستغرب، تستطيعون معرفة صعوبة المهمة.
You can see his mental workload spike as he goes through this,
يمكنكم أن تروا ارتفاع جهده الذّّهني عند مروره،
as you would expect with something that requires
كما تتوقعون من أمر يتطلب
this level of complexity.
هذا المستوى من التعقيد.
But what's really interesting is to look at areas of the track
ولكن ما يثير الاهتمام حقاً هو النظر في مناطق المضمار
where his mental workload doesn't increase.
حيث لا يزيد جهده العقليّ.
I'm going to take you around now
سوف آخذكم في جولة الآن
to the other side of the track.
إلى الجانب الآخر من الطريق.
Turn three. And John's going to go into that corner
وسوف يذهب جون إلى تلك الزاوية
and the rear end of the car is going to begin to slide out.
وسوف يبدأ الجزء الخلفي من السيارة في الانزلاق.
He's going to have to correct for that with steering.
يجب على جون تصحيح ذلك بالتوجيه.
So watch as John does this here.
لذلك شاهد ما يفعله هنا.
Watch the mental workload, and watch the steering.
شاهد الجهد الدماغيّ، وشاهد التوجيه.
The car begins to slide out, dramatic maneuver to correct it,
تبدأ السيارة بلإنزلاق، مناورة شديدة لتصحيح ذلك،
and no change whatsoever in the mental workload.
ولا تغيير على الإطلاق في الجهد العقلي.
Not a challenging task.
ليست مهمة صعبة.
In fact, entirely reflexive.
وفي الواقع، انعكاسي تماما.
Now, our data processing on this is still preliminary,
الآن، معالجة البيانات مازالت أولية،
but it really seems that these phenomenal feats
ولكن يبدو فعلا أن هذه الأعمال الإستثنائية
that the race car drivers are performing
التي يقوم بها سائقي سيارات السباق
are instinctive.
هي غريزيّة.
They are things that they have simply learned to do.
وهي أشياء قد تعلمّوا ببساطة القيام بها.
It requires very little mental workload
يتطلّب الأمر القليل من الجهد العقلي
for them to perform these amazing feats.
لأداء هذه الأفعال مذهلة.
And their actions are fantastic.
وأعمالهم رائعة.
This is exactly what you want to do on the steering wheel
وهذا بالضبط ما تريد القيام به على عجلة القيادة
to catch the car in this situation.
للسيطرة على السيارة في هذه الحالة.
Now, this has given us tremendous insight
الآن، أعطانا هذا بصيرة هائلة
and inspiration for our own autonomous vehicles.
وإلهاما للمركبات الذاتية الخاصة بنا.
We've started to ask the question:
بدأنا بطرح السؤال:
Can we make them a little less algorithmic
هل يمكننا أن نجعلهم أقل حسابياً
and a little more intuitive?
و أكثر بديهية؟
Can we take this reflexive action
يمكن أن نتّخذ هذا الإجراء الإنعكاسي
that we see from the very best race car drivers,
الذي نراه من أفضل سائقي سيارات السباق،
introduce it to our cars,
و ندرجه إلى سياراتنا،
and maybe even into a system that could
وربما حتى في نظام يمكنه
get onto your car in the future?
الدخول على سيارتك في المستقبل؟
That would take us a long step
هذا سوف ينقلنا خطوة طويلة
along the road to autonomous vehicles
إلى المركبات الذاتية
that drive as well as the best humans.
التي تقود جيداً كما يقود البشر
But it's made us think a little bit more deeply as well.
ولكن هذا جعلنا نفكرأكثر بعمق، أيضاً.
Do we want something more from our car
هل نريد شيئا أكثر من سيارتنا
than to simply be a chauffeur?
أكثر من أن تكون ببساطة سائقا؟
Do we want our car to perhaps be a partner, a coach,
هل نريد سيارتنا ربما أن تكون شريكا، مدربا،
someone that can use their understanding of the situation
شخصا ما يمكنه استخدام فهمه للحالة
to help us reach our potential?
لمساعدتنا على بلوغ قدراتنا الكامنة؟
Can, in fact, the technology not simply replace humans,
في الحقيقة هل يمكن للتكنولوجيا ببساطة عدم تبديل البشر
but allow us to reach the level of reflex and intuition
ولكن تسمح لنا الوصول الى مستوى من الانعكاس و الحدس
that we're all capable of?
كلنا قادرين عليه؟
So, as we move forward into this technological future,
لذا، ونحن نمضي قدما في هذا المستقبل التكنولوجي،
I want you to just pause and think of that for a moment.
أريدك أن تتوقّف وتفكر في تلك اللحظة
What is the ideal balance of human and machine?
ما هو التوازن المثالي بين الإنسان والأله؟
And as we think about that,
ونحن نفكر في ذلك.
let's take inspiration
دعونا نأخذ الألهام
from the absolutely amazing capabilities
من القدرات المدهشة
of the human body and the human mind.
للجسم البشري والعقل البشري.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)